<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Petition humbly presented to his Highnesse the Lord Protector, and to the High-Court of Parliament, the supream governors of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, with the dominions thereunto belonging. By divers ministers for the establishment of themselves and others their brethren (for their own lives) in the places to which they were admitted to officiate (as ministers of the gospel) without institution or induction from the bishops. With reasons thereto annexed whereof the contents are set down in page next after the petition. And at the end of the book an epistle to the sincere and pious preachers of the word of God written before the beginning of Parliament by Philotheus Philomystes.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E820_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207349</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866406</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866406</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118678</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90571)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118678)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 125:E820[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Petition humbly presented to his Highnesse the Lord Protector, and to the High-Court of Parliament, the supream governors of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland, with the dominions thereunto belonging. By divers ministers for the establishment of themselves and others their brethren (for their own lives) in the places to which they were admitted to officiate (as ministers of the gospel) without institution or induction from the bishops. With reasons thereto annexed whereof the contents are set down in page next after the petition. And at the end of the book an epistle to the sincere and pious preachers of the word of God written before the beginning of Parliament by Philotheus Philomystes.</title>
                  <author>Philomystes, Philotheus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw. Brewster at the Signe of the Crane in Pauls Churchyard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLIV. [1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 18.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118678:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PETITION Humbly preſented to his HIGHNESSE the LORD PROTECTOR, AND TO THE High-Court of PARLIAMENT, THE Supream Governors of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> with the Dominions thereunto belonging. BY DIVERS MINISTERS FOR THE Eſtabliſhment of themſelves and others their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (for their own Lives) in the places to which they were admitted to officiate (as Miniſters of the Goſpel) without Inſtitution or Induction from the Biſhops. WITH Reaſons thereto annexed whereof the CONTENTS are ſet down in the Page next after the PETITION. And at the end of the Book an Epiſtle to the Sincere and Pious Preachers of the Word of God written before the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Parliament By PHILOTHEUS PHILOMYSTES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ACTS 1.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And they praied, and ſaid, Thou Lord which knoweſt the hearts of all men, ſhew. whether of theſe two thou haſt choſen.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edw. Brewſter</hi> at the Signe of the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. MDCLIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:118678:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118678:2"/>
            <head>To his Highneſſe the LORD PROTECTOR, AND To the High Court of PARLIAMENT, The Supream Governours of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of the Dominions thereto belonging.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>The Humble Petition of diver Miniſters of the Engliſh Nation for themſelves and others their Brethren.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>THat your <hi>Petitioners</hi> (by Authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) <hi>appointed</hi> to preach the Goſpel in divers Congregations, from which the former Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bents were by the ſame Authority removed for their ſcandal and diſaffection to Reformation both Civil and Religious, have by them and the people (leavened by their unſound doctrine and prevaricating practiſe been harſhly entertained and injuriouſly dealt withall by manifold both perſonall and real wrongs, and ſome of us may truly adde to our complaint the threats and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of ſome of them to take away our lives; For none other cauſe that we can conceive, but 1. for that in the great diviſions of our Nation, our judgements and conſciences divided us from them and their party. 2. Becauſe we <hi>diſuſe</hi> the Service book and other ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious formalities (eſpecially cuſtomary and promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous Communions at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtmas Holidaies</hi> as they commonly call them;) and 3. for that we preſs the preciſe and pious obſervation of the Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath or Lords Day, and the daies of occaſional Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation
<pb facs="tcp:118678:3"/>and Thankſ giving, as alone obliging the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience under the ſtate of the Goſpel. And laſtly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they take us to be but unlawful intruders into the Rights of their outed Miniſters, for that our tenure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines not with our own but with their lives; and we are ordered to pay a fiſth part of the Sequeſtred Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, toward the maintenance of their Wives and Children, as part of their Revenue; for if the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents were dead, wherby their Widows and Orphans might have more need, no part or portion ſhould be aſſigned unto them, though they were not guilty of ſuch ſcandalous offences againſt God and man as their Husbands and Fathers have been.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it pleaſe your Highneſſe and this moſt Honourable Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, weighing the Premiſes with the Reaſons hereunto annexed, in ſuch a way as your prudence and goodneſſe ſhall direct you, to trke a courſe for a redreſſe and reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to the grievances fore-mentioned; ſo that ſo many of us (your Petitioners) as have continued conſtant to our Miniſterial duties both for preaching and practice, and faithful to the cauſe of Religion, and the peace and welfare of our Nation, with others our Brethren, who by the great Seal or the authority of private Patrons have been admitted to miniſterial Offices ſince the depoſition of Biſhops, may be confirmed in the places where we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide and officiate, for term of our natural lives (unleſſe we deſerve by any manner of miſcarriage to be caſt out of the favour and protection of publike Authority) and may be inveſted with the like power and priviledge both to require and recover the sights of our perſonal Incumbencies, which others have enjoied upon their preſentations to them by them by the Title of Patronage, and inſtitution &amp; induction by Biſhops in former times.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>And your Petitioners ſhall humbly pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:118678:3"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE Following DISCOURSE.</head>
            <list>
               <label>SECT. I.</label>
               <item>A neceſſary Caution premiſed againſt the conceit of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality to our ſelves and injury to others, four Reaſons for the Minister ſettlement where the Parliament pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him; The firſt drawn from the Parliament,<note place="margin">Reaſon <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> the ſecond from the people to whom he is ſent,<note place="margin">Reaſon <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> the third from himſelf; the fourth from the evil effects of his remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val,<note place="margin">Reaſon <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> in regard of others both goed and bad. <hi>Pag. 1.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reaſon <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. II.</label>
               <item>The fifth Reaſon againſt the preſent Miniſters diſſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Patron,<note place="margin">Reaſon <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> taken from the practice of primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive antiquity moſt contrary to it. <hi>p. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. III.</label>
               <item>The Sixth Reaſon taken from the diſtinction of Pariſhes,<note place="margin">Reaſon <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> when and by whom it was made. <hi>p. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. IV.</label>
               <item>The ſeventh Reaſon taken from the Original right,<note place="margin">Reaſon <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and duty of Patrons, and from the corruption of many Patrons, and their abuſe of Patronages, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb facs="tcp:118678:4"/>in <hi>England,</hi> both before the Parliament ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by the late King, and ſince. <hi>p. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. V.</label>
               <item>The reſpect due to Religious Patrons, with advice for a Conſciencious diſcharge of the truſt repoſed in them; wherein ſome paſſages in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Prinnes</hi> late Book (of the Right of Patronage) ſeeming to prejudice our cauſe, are propoſed and anſwered. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>SECT. VI.</label>
               <item>The Concluſion briefly recollecting the chief contents, of what is before more largely delivered. <hi>p. 20.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118678:4"/>
            <head>REASONS Humbly offered to the pious and judicious Conſideration of his Highneſſe the LORD PROTECTOR, and of the High Court of PARLIAMENT, why an able, painfull, and faithfull Miniſter (placed by the Supream power of this Nation in the room of a Delinquent Sequeſtred for Scandal and diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the State) ſhould not after the Delinquents death be diſplaced, upon pretence of the right of Patronage, to preſent another in his ſtead, if (until then) he have perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a ſincere and conſcientious execution of his office.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> A neceſſary Caution premiſed againſt the conceit of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality to our ſelves and injury to others, four Reaſons for the Ministers ſettlement where the Parliament pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him; The firſt drawn from the Parliament, the ſecond from the people to whom he is ſent, the third from himſelf; the fourth from the evil effects of his remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, in regard of others both good and bad.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough we conceive ſuch a Miniſter (as above-mentioned) ought to be confirmed in his Incumbency during life (his own life, not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others) yet as we would not have him ſtand upon the fickle terms of <hi>durante bene-placito:</hi> (either in reſpect of the people or of any perſon claiming priviledge above them) ſo we deſire not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118678:5"/>that any of us ſhould enjoy any publique maintenance or countenance any longer then <hi>Quam diu bonè ſe geſſerit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. We profeſſe we are not of their minde,<note n="a" place="margin">An exact relation of the Proceedings and tranſactions of the late Parliament who were diſſolved <hi>Decemb.</hi> 12. 1653. p. 18. Printed 1654.</note> 
                  <hi>Who ſay, that Patrons Preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are one of the ſtrong holds of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and who <hi>when it was</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">The true ſtate of the Caſe of the Common-wealth, and in reference to the late eſtabliſhed Government by a Lord Protector and a Parliament, <hi>p.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (in an equitable way) that perſons of eminent piety and fidelity might be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to judge of ſuch Miniſters as ſhould be preſented by Patrons, would admit of no regulation (but running out into the extream) vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted away the whole right of preſentation by Patrons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We deſire not to debarre them or any of our Brethren of this Nation, of their rightful properties or juſt rights, which the Law doth give and conſcience may take, as we were not willing (without our demerit) to be voted out of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry;<note n="c" place="margin">Ibid. p. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> or <hi>out of our right as civil men;</hi> The name of Patron where it is not (as the Popes Holineſſe) <hi>titulus ſine re,</hi> is to us acceptable and venerable; and for thoſe who are worthy of it and act according to it, we honour them, and they may well deſerve that honour by their faithfulneſſe and zeal in promoting the Goſpel of Chriſt, protecting and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing the true Miniſters of it, and him againſt thoſe that oppoſe or deſpiſe them.</p>
               <p>But withall we crave leave (in a matter ſo much import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great good or hurt of ſouls (as Patronage doth, thereafter as the title and authority is uſed well or ill) to deal with all plainneſſe and fidelity, and to ſhew (for cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) what we finde amiſle, and to be amended or removed, as well as what (for uſe) we think may be approved and maintained.</p>
               <p>This premiſed to clear our intentions <hi>from all partiality</hi> to any of our Tribe (who make defection from their duty whether miniſterial or Chriſtian) and <hi>from injurious impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of any lawful priviledge that any Patrons may have, <hi>if it be uſed lawfully;</hi> We truſt our juſt deſires may finde acceptance with his Highneſſe and the Parliament for theſe Reaſons enſuing; which though they be of ſeveral ſorts,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118678:5"/>ſome of them pleading the piety, juſtice and equity of the Miniſters eſtabliſhment, where he was placed by publike au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (upon the diſplacing of the former Incumbent) ſome of them ſhewing the contrary evils that any other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron ſhould (without any juſt exception againſt him for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency, idleneſſe or ſcandal) be allowed to eject him when the outed Miniſter dieth, who underwent a civil death (before) by his Sequeſtration.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The firſt Sort of Reaſons.</head>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> The firſt Reaſon may be taken from the Parliament by whom the one was removed and the other authoriſed to offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate in his place; And in the Parliament two things are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, the one is their care to make choice of good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters more then can reaſonably be expected, or is uſually found in moſt private Patrons; The other their authority, which was of force to caſt the offender both out of office and Benefice, and the ſame power might have acted for the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents ſettlement after the Delinquents death, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe had done ſo if (in this caſe) ſuch as were Patrons and Parliament-men had (which would have been for their praiſe as well as for the Miniſters peace) put their own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt for this particular into the <hi>Self-denying Ordinance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obj.</hi> But though they might depart from their own Right, or ſuſpend the exerciſe of their own priviledge, they could not give away other mens: But that other Patrons might ſtill be free (upon the death of the precedent Perſon) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent another in his ſtead as they ſee good.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. A Patron (if he be true to his truſt) ſhall gain nothing (in point of profit by a new Preſentation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (in that reſpect) he loſeth nothing by confirming the preſent Incumbent for term of his life.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For the liberty of preſenting another man, the Patron might have it allowed him, in making a new choice, when the ſucceſſor of the former Miniſter dieth, who though he come into the Benefice later, may go out of the world ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then his Predeceſſor, and that may prove a priviledge ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a prejudice to him.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118678:6"/>
                  <p n="3">3. If the Parliament (without ſuch compenſation or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends) had made a vote for continuation as well as for col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Sequeſtred Benefice, upon the Miniſter of their own choice (as we humbly conceive they ought to have done) no Patron (that was not a Parliament man) would have preſumed to gainſay it, ſince he might ſee the exerciſe of Parliamentary power in a far greater matter, <hi>viz.</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving his Clerk of his livelihood by their Sequeſtration, and might feel more himſelf then the ſuſpenſion of his Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage (for one turn only) in the paiment of the military Seſſement, and in other ſorts of ſubmiſſion to the preſent power.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. In reſpect of the people; if the Parliament have made a good choice for them, it is very injurious to them to leave it to the power of particular perſons to deprive them of the benefit of a good Miniſter, and to expoſe them to the peril of a worſe in his place by his removal from them.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> 3. In reſpect of the preſent Incumbent, it cannot but be a great grievance to him when he hath incurred the offence of many ill-diſpoſed Pariſhioners (for their ſakes who ſet him a watchman over their ſouls) and for his ſake (whom they have diſplaced) hath been diſtaſted by thoſe who ſuperſtitiouſly dote upon forbidden formalities, and hate Reformation with perfect hatred, then upon the death of his greateſt enemy, for him to be made the chief mourner, by expoſing him to extream indigence, among them who will be more ready to inſult over him then to pity or relieve him, is ſuch a miſery to the reformed Miniſtry, as (though a former Parliament did not prevent it) we truſt the Lord Protector and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be pleaſed to remedy.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> 4. By theſe ill uſages of the people and miniſter, the hearts of the godly are made ſad, the hands of the wicked ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the progreſſe of the Goſpel hindred, the honour of God (in the ſight of man) reproached, Reformation retar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded or rather thwarted, while a meer humane and private intereſt is preferred before his glory and the peoples ſafety.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118678:6"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>5</label> The fifth Reaſon againſt the preſent Miniſters diſſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Patron, taken from the practice of primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive antiquity moſt contrary to it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>IT is contrary</hi> to the primitive practice of the pureſt times for the godly Chriſtians (of old) made the choice of a Miniſter one of their chiefeſt bnſineſſes of Religion, for as an eminent<note n="d" place="margin">Non eſt ullum praeſtautius aut ſautarius Dei. donum, quam ſincerus verbi divini miniſter: vero dona Dei non poſſunt aliter, quam per preces obti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neri. <hi>Gerard.</hi> L. Com. Tom <hi>6. p. 136.</hi>
                  </note> Writer obſerveth;) and (to the like purpoſe) ſpeak the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend<note n="e" place="margin">There being nothing (under heaven) of greater importance then the preaching of the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, you cannot but be very ſenfible of what weight and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment it is to take a right eſtimate of all that offer themſelves, and to paſſe a due ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of ſuch only as Chriſt himſelf would have admitted to that great emploiment. <hi>Merc. Politic.</hi> from Thurld. <hi>April</hi> 13. to Thurſd. <hi>April</hi> 20, 1554; Numb. 201. p. 3415.</note> Commiſſioners for appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of publique Preachers, <hi>there is not a more excellent and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutary gift of God</hi> (he meaneth by the Miniſtry of men) <hi>then a good and well qualified Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to Chriſtian People; Now the gifts of God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are to be ſued for by praier to him who maketh able Miniſters of the New Teſtament,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.6. and therefore the Church (in the Apoſtles time) uſed (upon this occaſion) to addreſſe their ſupplications to God, as <hi>Act.</hi> 1.24 &amp; 13.3. &amp; 14.23. According to this patern hath been the conſtant practice of thoſe (who were intruſted by the Parliament for triall of Miniſters to be ſent (as ſupplies) to the places whence De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents were removed; for they alwaies began their exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination with praier, and they and the godly people (if there were any ſuch in the Pariſhes whither they were ſent) joyned their praiers to God for the ſame purpoſe, and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſuch Miniſters as was ſent unto them by God for their good, whereby they and their people as joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by God in a religious way, they ſhould not by men be put aſunder, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.6. in a meer ſecular way, which hath no ſavour of Religion in it, we may ſay (in reſpect of ſome) in a very ſinful way, as we ſhall ſhew in the practiſe of divers Patrons in the fourth Section.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118678:7"/>
               <p n="2">2. After the Apoſtles times (for many hundreds of years) the Monopoly of Patrons was not heard of in the Chriſtian Church; for even Biſhops were ordinarily<note n="f" place="margin">Marc. Anton. dc Dominis de Reipubl. Eccl. <hi>l. 3. c. 3. p. 41. §. 40.</hi>
                  </note> choſen by the Clergy and People, which <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> proves by 33. Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which are founded on this Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iom of Reaſon and Juſtice, That <hi>which is of common concernment ought to be propoſed to common conſent, ond not to be left to the</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Quod ad omnes pertinet, quod omnes tangit, ab unius arbitrio pendere neutiquam debet. <hi>Gerard.</hi> l. Com. Tom <hi>6. p. 136.</hi> Co. <hi>2. p. 137.</hi> Col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>arbitrary pleaſure of one alone,</hi> which<note n="h" place="margin">In eligendis Epiſcopis diu ſua populo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertas fuit conſervata, nequis obtruderetur, qui non omnibus aecceptus fuit, hoc igitur in concilio Antiocheno v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tilum eſt, nequis invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ingereretur quod &amp; Leo primus diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confirmat. Ep. <hi>90. c. 2.</hi> Calv Inſtit. <hi>l. 4. c. 4. p. 417.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> alſo affirmeth (and confirmeth it) by a Canon of a Council at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and an Epiſtle of <hi>Leo</hi> the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Againſt this the<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar.</hi> de Chricis <hi>c. 7.</hi> Tom. <hi>2. p. 309.</hi> in <hi>8.</hi> Eſtius in <hi>l. 4.</hi> Sent diſt. <hi>24.</hi> Eckius de primatu Petri, <hi>l. 3. c. 28.</hi>
                  </note> Papiſts take many exceptions upon pretence of reaſon and teſtimony, their Reaſons are many of them feeble and frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and their Teſtimonies of ſmall authority, only one (of each ſort) is worthy of notice and anſwer: The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, that popular <hi>Elections are turbulent and tend to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and Faction:</hi> The Teſtimony is that of <hi>the Council of</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Concil. Laodicen. Can. <hi>13.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Tom.<hi>1. Concil. p. 298.</hi> Edit. Bin. Lutet. Pariſ. <hi>p. 1636.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Laodicea</hi> (which ſate about the year 320.) <hi>and would not permit the people to make choice of Biſhops or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> which<note n="l" place="margin">Fateor in Concilio Laodiceno optima ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cione conſtitutum, ne turbis Electio permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur; vix enim unquam evenit ut tot capita. &amp;c. <hi>Calv. Inſtit. l. 2. c. 4. p. 418. §.12.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth but commendeth, becauſe (ſaith he) <hi>it very rarely (or ſcarce at any time) cometh to paſſe that ſo many heads do agree in one ſenſe well to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any matter; But for this inconvenience there was</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>good remedy;</hi> For</p>
               <p n="1">1. The promiſcuous multitude were not permitted to manage the Election, and that was it which was forbidden in the forecited Canon of the Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> the ſame (in effect) is aſſerted by the<note place="margin">m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <hi>The Divine Right of the Goſpel-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry,</hi> par. 1. c. 8. pag. 125. where they propoſe and prove, That the Election of a Miniſter doth not belong wholly or ſolely to the major part of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregation.</note> Provincial Aſſembly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118678:7"/>of <hi>London</hi> in their late Learned Book of the <hi>Divine Right of the Goſpel-Miniſtry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The<note n="*" place="margin">This term Clorgy we uſe only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is beſt underſtood, not as miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applied by Papiſts or any other who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate it to themſelves, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diee of the juſt priviledge of all true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers who are clear (or the Lords lot and portion) as well as the Prieſts under the Old Teſtament, or Presbyters or Miniſters of the New.</note> Clergy by rule and order, that the Election might be orderly, made the firſt choice, and propoſed the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected perſon to the Magiſtrate or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate (if they were Chriſtian) if not, to the people who were profeſſed Chriſtians; if they had any juſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt the party propoſed, another was offered, and if the people made choice of any, the <hi>Clergy</hi> were to judge of their ſitneſſe or unfitneſſe, and to approve or diſlike of them as they ſaw cauſe; So that the laſt or compleat Election was not left to the people alone, nor they left out, or any one obtruded upon them without their conſent, and that they might conſent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch a man as did merit their acceptance, they were <hi>docendi &amp; ducendi</hi> to be taught and lead by thoſe who were better able to judge then themſelves, and who were (by no means) to ſuffer themſelves to be miſled by popular ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or perverſeneſſe: thus (in effect though in other words) have<note n="m" place="margin">Calv. Inſtit. <hi>ubi ante.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Calvin,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Spalat. <hi>de Reipub. Eccleſ.</hi> l. 3. c. 3. p. 414. §. 52.</note> 
                  <hi>Spalatenſis,</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Duaren. <hi>de Sac. Ecc. miniſt.</hi> l. 3. c. 11. fol. 59. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Dua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renus</hi> the<note n="p" place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Reynolds <hi>Yheſ.</hi> 5. p. 650. added to his conference with <hi>Hart.</hi>
                  </note> famous Lawyer (as D. <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> ſet him forth) reſolved, and thereby have avoided the Popiſh Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections before-mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>6</label> The Sixth Reaſon taken from the diſtinction of Pariſhes, when and by whom it was made.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="3">3. FOr a great part of this time there was no diſtinction of Pariſhes, and until they were diſtinguiſhed there was no Patron that had any ſuch priviledge as is now aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118678:8"/>
               <p>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tooker</hi> of the Fab. of the Church and Church-li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings p. 44.</note> D. <hi>Tooker</hi> and<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hooker</hi> Eccl. Pol. l. 5. p. 33.3.</note> M. <hi>Hooker</hi> referre the Originall of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochiall Partitions to Pope <hi>Evariſtius Anno Chriſti</hi> 112. but neither of them quote any authority for it; They that do name the Book called the <hi>Pontificiale</hi> of Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> who was Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> about the year 367. but that (ſay<note n="s" place="margin">Baron. Annal, Tom. <hi>4.</hi> ad An. <hi>384.</hi> num. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> and<note n="t" place="margin">Poſſea. Appar. Tom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. <hi>410.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Poſſevine</hi>) was not the Book of that <hi>Damaſus</hi> (but of another) nor was it the Book of any <hi>Damaſus</hi> at all, but of <hi>Anastaſius Bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ethecarius</hi> ſaith<note n="u" place="margin">Bellar. de Ecc. Script. <hi>p. 123.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and whoſe Book ſoever it was, it is (for divers untruths) diſapproved by<note n="w" place="margin">Baron. ubi ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius,</hi> and<note n="x" place="margin">Bin. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> cou. <hi>p. 61.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Binius;</hi> Others referre the Originall of this diſtinction to Pope <hi>Dionyfius</hi> Anno 261. as<note n="y" place="margin">Bin. ibid. <hi>p. 191.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> accounts, but<note n="z" place="margin">Baron. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> num. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> reckons <hi>Anno</hi> 270. But this<note n="a" place="margin">Baron. ubi auio.</note> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> reports rather as a Renovation in his time, or by him, then a new Inſtitution: Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,<note n="b" place="margin">Mr <hi>Seld.</hi> Hiſt. of Tythes, c. 9. <hi>p.</hi> 254, 255.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether the diviſion of Pariſhes were <hi>Anno</hi> 112. 261. or 270. or any time, before the Year 700. (if made by a Pope or any Prelate of inferiour degree) it makes nothing for the ſole priviledge of Patrons hitherto; for until the Year 700. (as M. <hi>Selden</hi> obſerverh) the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters lived with the Biſhops (who received the revenues of the Church within the compaſſe of their dioceſſe for themſelves and them) and were ſent out (by them) to preach and adminiſter the Sacraments in ſeveral places (as was thought moſt expedient) in this no Patron had any thing to do either with the Office or Benefice of a Miniſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>7</label> The ſeventh Reaſon taken from the Original right, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge and duty of Patrons, and from the corruption of many Patrons, and their abuſe of Patronages, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in <hi>England,</hi> both before the Parliament ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by the late King, and ſince.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="5">5. THE Learned and prudent Authour of the Hiſtory of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> conceiveth, the diviſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118678:8"/>of Pariſhes in many places to have began with the people, thus,<note n="b" place="margin">Hiſt. of the <hi>Counc. of Trent.</hi> l. 6. p. 498.</note> 
                  <hi>When a certain number of Inhabitants (having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the true faith) built a Temple for exerciſe of Religion, they hired a Miniſter, and did conſtitute a Church, which by the neighbours was called a Pariſh, and when the number was encreaſed, if one Church and Miniſter were not ſufficient, thoſe who were moſt remote did build another and fit themſelves better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">M. <hi>Selden</hi> ib. p. 259. Of this ſee alſo M. <hi>Priune de Jure Patronat.</hi> pag. 10.</note> Mr <hi>Selden</hi> maketh the like Obſervation, <hi>When Devotion</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>grew firmer, and moſt Lay-men</hi> (of fair Eſtates) <hi>deſired the Countrey reſidence of ſome Chaplains that might be alwaies ready for Chriſtian inſtruction of them, their Families and adjoyning Tenants, Oratories, and Churches began to be built, and were endowed with peculiar maintenance from the Founders for the Incumbents which ſhould there only reſide.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. From this foundation or mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance allotted to the Miniſter, the Founder or Benefactor had a<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh. Cal.</hi> Medul. lexici jurid. <hi>p 808.</hi> Col. <hi>1.</hi> Jus Cansuic. tit. <hi>38. c. 25.</hi> col. <hi>498.</hi> Jus Greg. <hi>23.</hi> Edit. an. <hi>1616.</hi> Juſtiniani Novel. <hi>123.</hi> Concil Trident. Seſſ. <hi>14. c. 12.</hi> Tom. <hi>9. p. 391. Cowels</hi> Interpret. verbo Patrov. <hi>Duaren.</hi> de Sacr. Eecl. Miniſter. <hi>l. 5. fol 63. p. 6.</hi>
                  </note> Right of Patronage, and was called a Patron, rather a Patron then a Lord (ſaith<note n="e" place="margin">Dua en. <hi>Ibid fol.</hi> 64. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Duarenus</hi>) becauſe be was to be a <hi>Protector of the Church.</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Prinne de Jure Eatronat.</hi> p. 4 r.</note> 
                  <hi>by Plea, by interceſſion, by his tongue, by his pen, by his purſe, and by his ſword,</hi> and for both theſe Reaſons be had a double privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the <hi>one was to</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">See the Authors torecited; and adde to them M. <hi>Prinne de Jure Patronat.</hi> p. 10, 11, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>preſent a Clark when the Church was void,</hi> the <hi>other was</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Patronus houoraudus &amp; ab Eccleſia ſundard, ſuſtentandas ſtegeat, Loc. com. in jus canonicum ad fin. Corp Juris canon. verb Patronus.</note> 
                  <hi>to be relieved out of the revenues of the Church, if he (who was ſo religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly liberall, ſhould</hi> (which was very rarely and ſeldome ſeen) <hi>come to need the liberality of others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Theſe priviledges are held by<note n="i" place="margin">Eſt autem jus Patronatus perſonale, nec perſonam egredatur, niſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſit ratio quae in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Joh. Calv.</hi> Ned. lex jurid. <hi>p. 808.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>1.</hi>
                     <p>Nemo cujuſvis dignitatis Eccleſiaſtica vel ſecularis) quacunque ratione (niſi benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum aut capellam, de nove fundaverit, out erectam ſufficicute dote de ſuis proprijs &amp; patrimonialibus bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is competenter dotaverit) jus Patronatus imprtrare aut obtinere poſſit. Coc l. Trid. Seſ. <hi>14. c. 12.</hi> To. <hi>9. p. 391.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> ſome only perſon not hereditary, and ſo not to be transferred to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> mans heir (<hi>unleſſe fox the ſame reaſon that was in the Predeceſſor,</hi> that is): unleſſe he be a Founder or Benefactor alſo as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118678:9"/>he was; Others hold that the right of Patronage may paſſe from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as Lands of Inheritance) as<note n="k" place="margin">Notandum quod (mortus Patrono) id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. ad-haeredem ipſius tranfire, &amp; ſi plures exiſtunt Haereder in ſolidum Patroni eunt non pre partibus hereditarys. <hi>Fr. Duaren.</hi> de Eccl. Sacr. miniſt. <hi>l. 5. c. 4. fol. 64.</hi> a.</note> 
                  <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arenus</hi> reſolveth, and (with him) divers others, whoſe teſtimonies we ſhall no need to relate, fince we of this Nation have many Laws and long practiſe, for an hereditary right to a Title of Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, as well as of meer ſecular poſſeſſions, yet</p>
               <p n="8">8. The practice of divers Patrons hath been ſuch as hath ſhewed them to be rather titular then reall, many waies<note n="*" place="margin">Contra deteſtabilcm corruptelam Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronerum, qui (rectoribus Eccleſiarum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functis) Eccleſias ſpoliant. <hi>Concil. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisburg.</hi> An. Domint <hi>1420.</hi> Tom. <hi>7. par 7. p. 1147.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> for ſome <hi>(When the Rectors have been dead) have robbed their living Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of their Rights and Revenues,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Nonnulli Eccleſ. Patroni pueros infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; alios in Eceleſiis (in quibus jus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronatus obtinent) violenter intrudunt. Conc. <hi>Palentin.</hi> An. <hi>1332.</hi> Tom. <hi>7. par. 2. pag. 960.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and ſome have intruded children, yea, Infants in ſtead of able Paſtors,</hi> who could do no duty that others in their Names might take the dues belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Labourer in the work of the Lord, and thoſe who are guilty of theſe crimes will make no ſcruple (though it be a great ſinne) to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit<note n="m" place="margin">Quoniam in quibuſdam locis <hi>Alama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae</hi> fundatores Eccleſiarum, aut ipſorum Haeredes poteſtate abutuntur, clerices Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niace praeſentantes, <hi>&amp;c. Concil. Gerunden.</hi> Ann. <hi>1225.</hi> Tom. <hi>7.</hi> Conc. <hi>part. 2. can. 9. pag. 834, 835.</hi>
                  </note> Simony whereby they make a Miniſter to buy an inſupportable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then (the charge of ſouls) at ſuch an unreaſonable rate, as (if he live long) he ſhall never thrive or ſave by it, and (if he die ſoon) he is like to be a great loſer, by his hard bargain with his greedy Patron. Beſides what his loſſe may be at his account in another world, which is ſeldome thought of (by ſuch Simoniacal chapmen) until it come upon them to their confuſion.</p>
               <p n="9">9. We could wiſh that theſe complaints were (all of them) to be confined to forreign and Popiſh Patrons; But our condition is not ſo happy, for with us Proteſtants (ſuch Proteſtanrs as the Patrons of whom we now ſpeak are Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons) the ſinne of Simony is more allowed then it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Papiſts: For 1.<note n="n" place="margin">Append. ad Conoil <hi>Later. 3.</hi> Conc. <hi>par. 2. p. 673. Azor.</hi> Inſt. <hi>par. 3. pag. 12. c. 10.</hi> col. <hi>1690,</hi> Ibid.</note> They forbid and condemn the ſale of the right of Patronage. 2.<hi rend="sup">o</hi> If a man ſell any thing to which a Patronage is annexed, they judge it <hi>Simony to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118678:9"/>take any more for the purchaſe (with reſpect to the Patronage)</hi> then if there were no Patronage to paſſe along with it.</p>
               <p n="3">3.<note n="p" place="margin">Beneſleium (untequans vacat) nec dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, uec promittendum. <hi>Fr. Duaren.</hi> de Sac. eccleſ. miniſt. <hi>l. 5. c. 12. fol. 74. p. 6.</hi>
                  </note> They prohibited not <hi>only the ſale of Advowſons but the gift or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of any place before it be void,</hi> whereof the<note n="q" place="margin">Nulla Ecclefiaſtica miniſteria ceu Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficia tribuantur alicui, ceu promittantur, ne defidenare quis mortem proximi videatur, iu cujus locum &amp; beneficium ſe crediderit ſucceſſurum. Decret. <hi>Greg. l. 3. tit, 8.</hi> col. <hi>389.</hi>
                  </note> Canon Law rendreth this reaſon, <hi>leſt he ſhould deſire his death in whoſe place he had hope to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed;</hi> and the Biſhop of<note n="r" place="margin">Hiſt. of Councel of Trent. l. <hi>8. p. 764.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Conimbree</hi> (in the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi>) ſpeaking at large againſt expectations and advow. ſons, enforced his reaſon to a furtherdegree of danger then the deſire of death, and ſaid, <hi>they make the Incumbents death not only to be deſired but ſome times to be procured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (with us) Patronages are bought and ſold, not only as Appendices to other things that are purehaſed, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly and by themſelves, and the ſelling of advowſons avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as vendible<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſſets,</hi> So M. <hi>Pryn</hi> calleth them <hi>de Jure Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronatus,</hi> p. 14. The word <hi>Aſſets</hi> is nothing but the French word <hi>Aſſez</hi> i.e. <hi>ſatis.</hi> It ſignifieth in our common Law goods enough to diſcharge that burthen which is caſt upon the Executor or, Heir, in the ſatisfying of the Teſtators or Anceſtors debts or legacies. <hi>Cowels Interp. ver. Aſſets.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aſſets</hi> as well as either lands or chattels<note n="t" place="margin">Of this See the Copy of a Letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on that occaſion at the end of this Book.</note> , and that had been ſo decreed by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Parliament, and by their practice confirmed, if ſome mens votes might have prevailed to ſo ill a purpoſe, and with us the Sale of Benefices (actually void) hath been ſo frequent and ordinary, that there was need of a<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 40. of the Convocat. held 1603. the Oath is in theſe words following, 1 <hi>N. N.</hi> do ſwear, That I have made no Simoniacal payment, contract or promiſe, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly, by my ſelf or by any other, to my knowledge or with my conſent, to any perſon or perſons whatſoever, for or concerning the procuring and obtaining of this eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal dignity, place, preferment, office or living (reſpectively and particularly naming the ſame to which he is to be admirted, inſtituted, colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, inſtalled or confirmed) nor will (at any time) hereafter perform or ſatisfie any ſuch kinde of payment, conduct or promiſe, made by any other without my knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. So help me God through Jeſus Chriſt.</note> very ſtrict Canonical Oath to withhold Miniſters from buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, and as great need was there, and greater reaſon to put an Oath upon Patrons; that they ſhould not ſell them for the<note n="*" place="margin">M Prinne <hi>de Jure Patronatus,</hi> p. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>forfeiture of one turn only of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation</hi> (which is all the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our Law inflicteth upon a Simoniacal Patron) is too little,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118678:10"/>the Canon Law doometh him to no leſſe a loſſe, then (for his<note n="t" place="margin">Lindwood. <hi>Prov. conſtit.</hi> l. 5. fo. 202. p. 6.</note> whole life) to be deprived of the power of preſenting, but their priviledge hath found <hi>too many Patrons</hi> (hitherto in the Parliament) ſo that (as a choice darling) by whom it hath been too much cheriſhed to be reſtrained from all offence, and <hi>too many friends</hi> in Courts of juſtice to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed when abuſed, thence it is</p>
               <p n="10">10. That Patrons have put in ſo many unworthy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters who deſerved (by the Parliament to be put out again, and that they have ſometimes preſumed (by force of Arms) to pull thoſe out of their poſſeſſion,<note place="margin">At <hi>Aſtbury</hi> in <hi>Cheſh. An.</hi> 1658</note> whom both the Houſes of Parliament have (by their expreſſe approbation) choſen and placed in the room of diſplaced Delinquents, and that ſome have outed Miniſters of eminent note and publike ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, to make room for thoſe who (for their diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the State) have been expelled out of other places, and that others (as bad as they) have been (by Patrons) obtruded upon the people, and ſo (as they well deſerved) have been again removed by authority: In theſe and other kindes (very criminall) we doubt not but divers inſtances of miſcarriage of Patrons may be produced, which may be worthy both of the cognizance and correction of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream authority of this Nation.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The office of a Patron being to protect both the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent and people againſt injury (ſo far as he is able) without any expectation of advantage to himſelf, it is his duty to do what he can that the Church may be well ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied<note n="u" place="margin">M. <hi>Prinne de jure patronatus.</hi> p. 7, 11, 13, 13, 15, 21, 35.</note> in caſe of lawfull avoidance by death, reſignation, tranſlation, deprivation, or otherwiſe, but not to make it void when it is well ſupplied already, by putting out an able and learned Miniſter, that he may ſhew his power and act his pleaſure by impoſing another upon the people.</p>
               <p>Nor is there or can there be any thing in his priviledge (if rightly ſtated and not corruptly exerciſed) which may countervail the leaſt of the evils (before remembred and complained of) againſt the glory of God, the honour of the Government, the Right of the people and Miniſter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the one and accepted by the other (at leaſt by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118678:10"/>the godly party) for their ſpiritual guide in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>And in this caſe we conceive their priviledge (ſuch as it is) ſhould be leſſe prevalent for the expulſion of a good Miniſter who abuſed it before in the choice of a bad one, ſo bad that he deſerved to be expelled for diſ-ſervice to the Church and State, and therefore put a neceſſity upon the Superior powers to put him out and to chooſe another, who (continuing true to his undertaking) ſhould <hi>be continued in his place</hi> for the carrying of the work of Reformation, as it was deſigned by the Supreme authority of this Nation, which is deſerted and obſtructed by permitting a private Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron to drive an able, faithfull, and painfull Preacher from the Church to which he was ſent (by the higheſt authority, upon due and orderly triall of his ſufficiency and ſincerity) and <hi>to put in another</hi> (of his own Nomination) to ſucceed the dead in his Title and the living in the Office and Benefice annexed to it, which a faithfull and godly Patron would not do if he might, and an unfaithful and wicked Patron ſhould not be permitted to do if he would.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> The reſpect due to Religious Patrons, with advice for a Conſciencious diſcharge of the truſt repoſed in them; wherein ſome paſſages in Mr <hi>Prinnes</hi> late Book (of the Right of Patronage) ſeeming to prejudice our cauſe, are propoſed and anſwered.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE do not by all or any of this we have ſaid, intend any prejudice to ſuch Patrons as (by Law) are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to take care and provide a well-qualified Preacher for a People that want him, and who ſhew themſelves conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enciouſly carefull to promote the glory of God and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good of Chriſtian Congregations, preferring them before their own temporall intereſt; Such a Patron we take
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118678:11"/>for a Patron indeed, that is, a<note n="u" place="margin">Accipitur Patrouns pro defenſore corum quos in tutela habet. <hi>And. Altiat.</hi> de verb. ſignif. Commont. leg. <hi>52. p. 129.</hi>
                  </note> defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which implieth as<note n="x" place="margin">M. <hi>Prinne</hi> de jure patronatus, <hi>p. 4.</hi>
                  </note> M. <hi>Prin</hi> hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>not only a Patronage Protection, or defence of the Incumbents and Churches cauſe, when there is need in Courts of Juſtice, by</hi> way of plea <hi>or interceſſion, as an Advocate doth, but alſo their defence and Patronage,</hi> by the ſword, <hi>in the field when aſſaulted by open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed adverſaries, ſacrilegious Church-robbers, or blourly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors;</hi> by pen, <hi>when invaded by hereticks and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichs;</hi> Such a Patron well deſerveth to be honoured (as the Civilians<note n="*" place="margin">Primum lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum (poſt patrem apud cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entem) obtinere patronus debet. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                  </note> teach us) <hi>next unto a Father;</hi> and we conceive he may be of good uſe for the choice of a meet Miniſter, and for his comfortable Incumbency (when he is choſen) as alſo for the prevention of diſcord, and for quiet compoſing thereof (if it ariſe among the people about the Election of a Miniſter) and that when ſuch a one as is not liable to any iuſt exception, (for inſufficiency or ill carriage) is by ſuch a Patron ſeaſonably offered to the people (that is, when the place becometh void by death, reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) as hath been ſaid of him who officiated to them before, he ſhould rather be chearfully received, then waywardly rejected by them, which hath<note n="w" place="margin">Peccant Eccleſiae quae perſonam a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouis nominatam, teſtimonio conſiſtorij com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatam, donis ad doccndum neceſſarijs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructam, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> recipere reeuſant, urgentes ut plures una perſonae praeſententur in arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio enim Patrouorum poſitum, an unam vel plures perſonas nominare velint, nes abſolutae neceſſicatis eſt, ex pluribus fieri electionem, ſed ſuffieit ad legitim an vocationem ſi acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat Eccleſiae conſenſus: — a Patrono nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ium &amp; a conſiſtorio comprobatum populus denegare non debet, niſi ob graves ac praeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes cauſas, doctrinam vel vitam praelen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatae perſonae concernentes. <hi>Gerard.</hi> loc. com. vol. <hi>6. c. 3. Sect. 6. col. 137.</hi>
                  </note> ſometimes been the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples fault, who have refuſed ſuch as have been worthy to be accepted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſingly propoſed by the Patron without others out of whom they might take their choice of him they like beſt.</p>
               <p>Which diſreſpect of a worthy and well-meaning Patron is deſervedly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked and condemned by a Learned Authour fore-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for it is very conſiderable which<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>M.</hi> Prinne de Jure pat. <hi>p, 10, 11.</hi>
                  </note> M. <hi>Prinne</hi> hath in his late Book of the <hi>Right of Patronage</hi> (though in all points we agree not with him, and in ſome particulars conceive we have juſt cauſe to except againſt him) in theſe words, <hi>Now becauſe both the ſoil whereon theſe Churches were built, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118678:11"/>with the Church-yards thereto annexed for interring the dead, theſe Fabricks of the Churches, with the Parſonage-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Rectories, Glebes, Revenues, and Tithes thereto annexed, for the Miniſters maintenance, proceeded originally from theſe Founders Piety and Donation, and no way from the Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners who were but the Founders Tenants Servants or Children, and held their Lands from by or under them, charged with ſuch Tithes as they firſt granted out of them to the Miniſters (ſtill allowed to them in their Leaſes, Fines, Purchaſes, in all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages by a proportionable defalcation, according to their ordinary valuation) both by the common, Canon, and civil law, to the Laws of our own and other Realms, and the very dictates of Reaſon, Juſtice, Equity, held it reaſonable, juſt, equitable, that theſe pious, bountifull Founders and Benefactors ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the full and abſolute power of beſtowing, conferring the Rectories, Tithes, and profits of theſe Cburches (upon every avoidance by death, reſignation,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ceſſein</hi> ſeems to be allied in ſigniſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to <hi>Ceſſor,</hi> and <hi>Ceſſor</hi> is he that ſo long ceaſeth or neglecteth to perform a duty belonging to him, as that by his <hi>ceſſe</hi> or <hi>ceſſing,</hi> he incurreth the danger of Law, and hath or may have the Writ <hi>Ceſſavit</hi> brought againſt him. <hi>Old nat. brev.</hi> p. 126. <hi>Cowels Interp. verb.</hi> Ceſſor.</note> 
                  <hi>Ceſſein, tranſlation, deprivation, or otherwiſe) on ſuch Incumbent Miniſters as themſelves, their Heirs and Aſſigns, ſhould nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and make choice of for their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Chaplains, it being held both unjuſt and unreaſonable, unconſcionable, injurious and ungratefull, that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners or other ſtrangers (who contributed nothing towards the Fabricks Soil or Endowments of theſe Churches, and paid no Tithes but what originally proceeded from the Patrons Grants, allowed to themin their Fines and Purchaſes) ſhould deprive them of or intercommon with them, in their Right of preſentation, upon any avoidance, it being the Founders meer courteſie, piety, favour, to admit them and their poſterities free acceſſe at all times to theſe Churches, which they founded not, and to reap the ſpirituall benefit of theſe Miniſters and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which they maintained not at their own free coſt, but theſe Founders and Patrons only; As it is (at this day) a meer grace and favour in our Innes of Court, Colledges, and ſome Noblemen and Gentlemen in the Countrey, to permit their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hours and Strangers free acceſſe to their private Chappels in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118678:12"/>their houſes to the Ordinances here diſpenſed by their own hired Chaplains and Preachers,</hi> So far M. <hi>Prinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have reported his opinion of the Patrons Right and power in preſentations at length; That it may appear we do him right, in what he ſaith well, and that we do him no wrong when we except againſt that wherein (we conceive) he hath ſaid amiſſe.</p>
               <p>For we grant the Right of a Fundamentall Patron, or of a Patron that is a Founder of or a great Benefactor to a Church, is much in that Church ſo founded and endowed by him, but <hi>we do not couccive</hi> that they who were never ſuch as either of them, cannot have a full and abſolute power of beſtowing and conferring Rectories, Benefiees, Tithes, and profits of Churches, upon every avoidance, on ſuch Incumbent Miniſters as themſelves, their Heirs and Aſſigns alone ſhall nominate and make choice of for their Miniſters and Chaplains, <hi>neither do we think</hi> there is as good juſtice and equity for his propriety of Right for ſole Election who is neither Founder nor Benefactor, as for his who builded a Church or houſe upon his own Land, at his own coſt, and endowed them with glebe-lands, and Tithes to diſpoſe of them to whom he thinks meet, without the Licence of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who have no intereſt nor Inheritance therein, as<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>M.</hi> Prinne de Jure pat. <hi>p. 11, 21.</hi>
                  </note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Prinne</hi> affirmeth: Nor can we imagine that ſo good and learned a man, ſo good a Friend to godly and learned Miniſters, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Prinne,</hi> would be advocate for any Patrons who would not rather uſe his power to confirm an able and Religious Miniſter in his place, then to eject him (upon this pretence) that by the Law he hath a peculiar and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnlar Right ſo to do.</p>
               <p>For 1. (as M.<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>M.</hi> Prinnc de Jure par. <hi>p. 21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Prinne</hi> himſelf<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> p 35.</note> confeſſeth) the Patrons Right is not abſolute but limited by law to the choice of a fit perſon, a<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>convenient Miniſter,</hi> when the Church is void.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That fitneſſe is to be judged of by others, as himſelf (in effect) acknowledgeth, where he ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>that the evils and corrapt Contracts are ſufficiently prevented by the Laws already made againſt them (we wiſh it were ſo) and a vigilant
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118678:12"/>care of Governours and Presbyteries, to admit none but able, godly, and Orthodox perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Thoſe who founded Churches and endowed them out of devotion, gave them to God, and in regard of his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in them could not diſpoſe of them, could not diſpoſe of them as a man might do of a private or partieular houſe which he buileeth for a civil uſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the people have ſome more right in Churches then at the courteſie of Patrons, appears by this, they are by the Laws of the Land to repair the body of the Church at their charge, as the Rector or the Parſon is the Chancell at his charge, which could not be expected, nor would it be performed without (at leaſt) an implicit acknowledgement of a Right to make uſe of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But though they have a right to make uſe of the Church, they have no right to make choice of the Miniſter who is to officiate in it, and if the power were put into their hands (ſaith M. <hi>Prinne</hi>) 1. <hi>It would</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>M.</hi> Prinne do Jure pat. <hi>p. 27.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>cauſe faction and diviſion in every Pariſh upon every vacancy.</hi> 2.<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>The genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Pariſhioners and people (in moſt Pariſhes) are ſo ignorant, vicious, irreligious, injudicious, prophane, neglectful of Gods publike. Ordinances, and enemies to all ſoul-ſearching and ſoul-ſaving Miniſters, who would ſeriouſly reprove and withdraw them from their fins and evil courſes, that we may ſooner finde an hundred conſciencious, religious, and godly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons (careful to preſent and encourage ſuch Miniſters) then one ſuch Pariſh wherein the generality and ſwaying part of the people, are ſo well-affested and qualified as ſuch Patrons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The right of the people (as we have already ſhewed) is more in the admiſſion of the Miniſter then in poſſeſſion of the place where he performeth his Function, and a right of ſo much more moment, that it were better for them to hear a good Miniſter in the open Air (as at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe the uſe hath been heretofore) then a bad one under the ſhelter of a ſeeled or leaded Church-roof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it would go ill with Religion if the choice of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteers were to be ſwayed by the choice of the generality of Pariſhioners, or the major part: ſo we fear it would not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118678:13"/>go very well with it if there were an abſolute power in the generality of Patrons, to Place what Miniſters they pleaſe over our Chriſtian Congregations, and to diſplace them at their pleaſure, Thereſore</p>
               <p n="5">5. As we would not have the Patrons power abſolute, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially not ſo far as to be able to diſplace an able and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Miniſter ſet over a people by publike authority, ſo we would not have the rude or irreligious Rabble, to interpoſe in ſo pious an intereſt, nor the godly (who are beſt able to judge) waywardly to conteſt with the Patron, when he propoſeth ſuch an one to them as neither by lack of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, utterance, diligence, and godlineſſe of life, is liable to exception. Nor would we have ſuch a Miniſter to ſleight the favour of the Patron (becauſe he is placed by a power fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to his) but rather by all ingenuous obſervance of him, and reſpect unto him, to endeavour the obtainment of his conſent to his ſettlement, and his countenance and his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection in the execution of his calling.</p>
               <p>And that Patrons may be more free from deſert of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt them then many heretofore have been, we wiſh them to take heed of taking <hi>gain for godlineſſe,</hi> as ſome do, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. and rather to think <hi>godlineſſe is gain,</hi> as the Apoſtle would have them, <hi>v.</hi> 6. and then they will not (for filthy lucres ſake) make ſale of that which ſhould be freely given. The Emperour <hi>Alexander Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus</hi> (no profeſſed Chriſtian<note n="f" place="margin">Chriſto Templum condere voluit, cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que inter Deos recipere, cumque Chriſtiani qui locumquendam qui publicus fuerat occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſent, &amp; popinarij dicerent ſibi eum deberi, reſcripfit, melius eſſc quomodocunque illic De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us colatur, quam locus popinarijs dedatur. <hi>Bueolz,</hi> Ind. Chron. ad An. <hi>224. p. 171.</hi>
                  </note> though a favourer of Chriſt and Chriſtian profeſſion) would not allow of the<note n="g" place="margin">Neceſſe eſt ut qui emit vendat, ego non patiar mercatores poteſtatum, quos ſi patiar soudemuare non poſſum, erubeſco enim punire illum bominem qui emit &amp; vendit. <hi>Elias Lamprid.</hi> de Alexandr. Sever. <hi>part. 3. Hiſt. Auguſt. p. 376.</hi> Edit. Boxborn.</note> ſale of ſecular offices, leſt they who bought their power by whole-ſale, ſhould ſell their conſciences by retail in the exerciſe thereof, wherein the injury could be but (as the office was) ſecular (relating only to the bodies, goods, or good name of another) but buying and ſelling ſpirituall offices may produce ſo much worſe effects as the things are the better and more precious (the glory of God and the ſouls
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118678:13"/>of men) moſt prejudiced by ſuch Simoniacal merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore Patrons ſhould do well, to take the good counſel of h M. <hi>Hooker</hi> (though no Preciſian) he cals it <hi>a Requeſt and moſt earneſt Suit,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>That they who have a Right to Patronage, have power to preſent to ſpirituall livings, and may in that reſpect much damnifie the Church of God (for the eaſe of their own acccunt in that dreadfull day) would ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what conſider what it is to betray (for gain) the ſouls which Chriſt hath redeemed with his bloud, what to violate the ſacred bond of fidelity and ſolemn promiſe given (at firſt) to God and his Church, by them from whoſe original (together with the ſelf Title of Right) the ſame obligation of duty is likewiſe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This grave and godly advice as it behoveth all Patrons ſeriouſly to conſider and conſtantly to practiſe, ſo it laieth ſo much the greater Engagement upon Academical and Collegiat Patrons, as the<note n="i" place="margin">In caſe of recuſancy, Popiſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons (during their recuſancy only) are diſabled to preſent or grant any avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of any Churches or Eccleſiaſticall Livings after conviction. <hi>cook</hi> 10. Rep. P. 55. and their right of preſentment granted to the Univerſties of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge.</hi> 3. <hi>Idcob.</hi> cap 5. cited by M. <hi>Prinne de iure patron.</hi> p. 18.</note> greater truſt is repoſed in
'them, and as they have the more choice are better able to judge, and are more obliged to look directly to the gracious and glorious ends for which the Miniſtry is ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and for ſuch Patrons though here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore (conferring Benefices rather by tale of years then weight of parts) they too frequently ſent forth unworthy men to take upon them tae charge of ſouls, yet in the worſt of times they were ſeldome guilty of the ſinne of Simony (as moſt other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons were:) but now there is leſſe fear of that, and more hope that for time to come collegiat preſentations will be ſwayed not by ſeniority but ſufficiency, and not by Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alone by Religion likewiſe, not to deprive a people of a good Miniſter when they have one, but to ſupply them with a good one when they want, not by meer imperious impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition upon the people, but by a Chriſtian and courteous compliance with their good likings, when juſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable things will give them content, and ſo it will be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118678:14"/>matter of great advantage to the Church, that ſuch pious, judicious, and meek-ſpirited Patrons be ſtill continued in their truſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p> The Concluſion briefly recollecting the chief contents, of what is before more largely delivered.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. IF the Parliament, profeſſing and acting Reformation of matters amiſſe in Church and State, be juſtly to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted more circumſpect and carefull, what Paſtors they ſet up over Chriſtian Congregations, then ordinary Patrons may reaſonably be preſumed to be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If when the Parliament hath made a good choice of a Paſtor for ſuch a people, and they have accepted of him, and are deſirous to have him continue with them, they ſhould not be deprived of him at the will and pleaſure of one man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the Miniſter appointed to officiate by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be expoſed to the hatred of the outed Miniſter and all his party, and to all the injuries and indignities they can do him, for his faithfull and conſtant cleaving to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and for his conformity to their Ordinances againſt ſinful prophaneſſe and ſuperſtitious formality.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If when the Sequeſtred Miniſter dieth, the thruſting out of ſuch a one by the Patron that he may put in another whom he pleaſeth in his place be to give him up to miſery, among them that hate him, and to make him the principall mourner at his chief enemies death, and this to the grief of the godly, the rejoycing of the wicked, and to the great Reproach and Impediment of the Reformation pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If the primitive Chriſtians (of the pureſt times) made the choice of an Evangelicall Miniſter not a matter (meerly or principally) of humane management, but one of the chiefeſt buſineſſes of Religion, to be guided and ordered by
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118678:14"/>an eſpecial providence of God, and that to be ſought for and obtained by praier.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If for many hundreds of years after Chriſt the Church had no ſuch preſentative Patrons as in later ages have born all the ſway, but that <hi>matters of common concernment in the Church</hi> (as the choice of a Miniſter is) were to be carried on by common conſultation, and as much as may be alſo by conſent.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If when Patronage began, ſuch only were rightly ſo called and accounted, as were Founders of Churches, and enowed them with competent Revenues, or were (ſome way or other) great benefactors unto them.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If the office of a Patron be to be carefull to ſupply a Congregation with a good Miniſter, when there is want of one, and not to deprive the people of a good one when they have him, and by all good waies and means to uphold and countenance him in his office, and to maintain the Rights and Priviledges of the Church committed to his care.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If a Patron may not ſell either a preſentation or an advowſon, nor make any ſecular advantage of his Right or Truſt, as a true religious Patron will not though he might gain never ſo much by the bargain.</p>
               <p n="10">10. If Suſpenſion of a Patron from one turn of preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only at the death of the <hi>former,</hi> may be recompenſed by permitting him to preſent at the death of the <hi>later In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent,</hi> and that in all likelihood by a ſpeedier return, when an ancient man is placed in the room of a younger; or if (without ſuch compenſation) one turn were wholly loſt to him, the inconvenience were nothing ſo great as the miſchiefs ſore-mentioned on the Miniſters part, and theirs who are intereſted in him, if he ſhould be ejected, becauſe it is the Patrons pleaſure to have it ſo.</p>
               <p n="11">11. If the Prevarication of divers particular Patrons, and the abuſe of their power and truſt, have been ſuch in this Nation (eſpecially by the ſinne of Simony) as to need ſevere Laws and Ordinances to reſtrain it.</p>
               <p n="12">12. If ſo many, ſet up for Overſeers or Watchmen for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118678:15"/>the ſafety of ſouls, by ſuch Patrons (though all were not ſuch, for divers were rather unhappy then ungodly in the choice of their Clerks) deſerved to be put out for inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, idleneſſe, ſcandal and diſaffection to the Parliament, and thoſe whom they have ſent to ſucceed them in their places, continue conſtant in the duties of their callings, both general as Chriſtians, and particular as Miniſters, and as Subjects to the Supream Governours of this Nation; Then we truſt that their wiſedom duely weighing all the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (which before have been propoſed and proved) will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conclude our Requeſt to be reaſonable, and their goodneſs will reſolve to take us ſo farre into their honourable and powerful protection, as to ſecure us in our Incumbency while we live, and endeavour ſincerely and conſcienciouſly to diſcharge our duties to God and his people, from the reward of ſuch as like <hi>unſavoury ſalt</hi> deſerve to <hi>be caſt ont, and to be trodden under foot of men,</hi> Mat. 5.13. which though we conceive no Patron (who can juſtly challenge the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and truly perſormeth the truſt of a Patron) will think us worthy of, yet ſince we have no ground of hope that the moſt are ſuch as they ſhould be, we may have juſt cauſe of fear leſt it may be the lot of divers among us to be hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dealt withall, if we fall into ſome of their hands (ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially theirs who in their Principles and practiſe as farre as they dare, are as oppoſite to the preſent Magiſtracy as to our Miniſtry) for of ſuch we may expect to ſuffer both for their ſakes and for our own; Sure we are we have the more enemies, and our enemies are the more ſpightfull againſt us, and more ready to wrong us by all the waies they have in their power (as in part we have touched in our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition,) Becauſe
<list>
                     <item>1. We <hi>adhered</hi> to the Parliament, while they ſo farre as their power and courage carried them, oppoſed it, and <hi>obeyed</hi> the authority thereof in ſubmitting to ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands as are rather conformable then contrary to the Word of God, which they deny and diſobey as boldly as if the government that is over them, had nothing to do with them but to protect them in a priviledge to ſay and do what they pleaſe.</item>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:118678:15"/>
                     <item>2, We do not admit of ſuch promiſcuous Communions as make no difference between the clean and unclean, as there ſhould be <hi>Eze.</hi> 22.26. to which confuſion the common people have been ſo accuftomed (eſpecially at <hi>Eaſter</hi>) that they think we do them more wrong in denying them the Sacramental bread and wine at that time (though for groſſe ignorance or open ſcandall) then they can do us though they defraud us of our dues throughout the whole Year.</item>
                     <item>3. We do not officiate by the Service-Book, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them ſo much dote on, that we fear it would offend them more to be deprived of it then if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble were taken from them.</item>
                     <item>4. We are more ſtrict in our doctrine and practiſe, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sabbath, and other points of Chriſtian piety, and are more zealous againſt the Superſtitious and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane obſervances which meet together (though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe oppoſite) in their unchriſtian Chriſtmas Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellings then our Predeceſſors have been.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>By all which as we are made the objects of a deeper de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of hatred by our adveſaries, ſo we hope (for the ſame cauſes) we ſhall be accounted the more capable of his Highneſſe and the Parliaments compaſſion for prevention of that evil which may befall us if we ſurvive our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and ſucceed them not in the favour of the Patron, to ſettle us where (by authority of Parllament) we were formerly placed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:118678:16"/>
               <head>The Copy of the Letter mentioned in the <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                  </hi> Section at the Letter <hi>(t)</hi> in the margine of the <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                  </hi> Alphabet.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Right Honourable, and my very good Lord,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Shall firſt deſire to repreſent my moſt affectionate and humble ſence of the favour your Lordſhip ſheweth me, and of the honour you do me, in that (at ſo little leiſure as your many and weighty affairs will allow you) you are pleaſed not only to beſtow ſo many lines upon me at once, but in them both to inſtruct me what to think, and hope of our preſent <hi>Optimates,</hi> and to chear me up in my many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts with the <hi>Peſſimates</hi> of theſe; by a promiſe of more frequent exchange of Letters with me in time to come: Though I ſhall not be ſo preſumptuous (in taking your word) as to expect a commerce with you (in this kinde) upon even returns, but only as it ſhall pleaſe your Lordſhip to take the occaſion and make the proportion. Next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you referre me to the Diurnals for common intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, I ſhall crave leave to preſent you with ſome thoughts and doubts I have concerning a report in the <hi>moderate,</hi> as the Authours miſcals his News-Book of this laſt week, in the laſt page of it, which he delivereth in theſe words, <hi>An Act for Sale of all Eccleſiaſtical Promotions in the gift of the Crown, great Seal,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which was twiſe read and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted;</hi> If he relate aright, ſomewhat (as I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) is wrong, at leaſt in the deſign of ſome, which if it ſhould proceed to accompliſhment (unleſſe it be leſſened with ſo many limitations as would bring it next to nothing) would eaſt a greater reproach upon our Reformation, then could fairly be cleared by the moſt able Apologiſt; for the Sale of Eccleſiaſtical Offices is condemned by Scripture, by reaſon, by humane conſtitutions of all ſorts, by the godly in all ages, and the better ſort of both Religions, Proteſtant and Papiſt. In the Title of this Act (as this man ſets it down in contrary terms of <hi>ſale and gift</hi>) there is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of a fault (at leaſt implicitly) and a profeſſion (in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118678:16"/>ance) of a more corrupt adminiſtration of Eccleſiaſticall matters then in the late Kings time, in ſetting that to open <hi>ſale</hi> which hath been and ſhould be beſtowed meerly as a <hi>gift:</hi> there is ſomething in our Laws I confeſſe (as your Lordſhip better knoweth then I) which permitteth the ſale and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of Eccleſiaſtical Patronages, and of advowſons; and ſo they permit Duels, Pluralities, Non-reſidence, but I hope the abolition of ſuch Laws will be a further degree of our departure from the corruption of Popery and Papal prelacy, and if the State will allow of ſuch ſcandalous traffick (but I hope it will never do ſo) their next act muſt be command them that have bought Eccleſiaſtical Benefices to give them freely to thoſe that are to officiate in the Church; as <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi>
                        <note n="k" place="margin">Dionyſius victoriolas aureas, &amp; Pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras coronaſque ſimulachrorum tollebant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ferunt haee quae dixi ſublata de fauis, in fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum protuliſse &amp; per praeconem vendidiſſe, exactaque pecunia edixiſſe, ut quod quiſque a ſacris baberet, id (aute diem certam) in ſuum quidque fanum referret. <hi>Cic.</hi> de Nat. deor. l. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>255.</hi> num. <hi>63.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>when he had ſpoiled the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens Temples of their riches, and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and had (by Proclamation of a Crier) ſold them in the market, and received money for them, gave charge to the buyers to reſtore them to the Tèmples from whence they were taken,</hi> to which Edict the Orator that reports it addes this <hi>Epiphonema,</hi>
                        <note n="l" place="margin">Ita ad impietatem it Dcos, in homines adjunxit injuriam. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>ſo to impiety againſt God he joyned injury againſt men,</hi> and how ſhall thoſe two be ſeparated in the ſale of ſuch things as (appertaining to Religion) ſhould be freely given for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions ſake? And if they ratifie their ſale ſo far as to allow men to ſell that which they have bought, that is a doubling, yea, a multiplying of the impiety, as oft as the alienati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch things paſſeth from hand to hand, which muſt needs amount to a greater guilt then of <hi>Dionyſius;</hi> for he (for ought we finde upon record) offended but once in that kinde, and preſently retracted the wrong done to Religion, by a Decree of Reſtitution of his Temple-ſpoils (though he reſtored not the money to them that bought them) as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it to be a leſſer crime to be injurious towards men then ſacrilegious toward God, wherein <hi>in Theſi</hi> he did not erre, though <hi>in hypotheſi</hi> (I grant) it was worſe ſo to defraud men then to take away the goods from ſuch Idol-gods, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118678:17"/>he took them for meer Idols and not for true gods whom he robbed; Your Lordſhip (I truſt) hath read thus farre with patience, ſince you know it is a ſervice of duty and charity to do all we can to prevent the evil of ſin, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. I muſt now leave it to your Lordſhips prudence, to make ſuch uſe of this advertiſement as juſt cauſe and fit occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may produce, hoping that if ſuch as are wiſe eſpie any errour in this plain-dealing of mine, they that are alſo pious will overlook it, with liking of that ſincerity which goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it, and ſhall ever accompany both the dictates and endeavours of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble and heartily devoted Servant, N.Y.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>May 29. 1649.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>It is probable this Letter might be ſome occaſion, of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to a non-plus this ſcandalous motion for the ſale of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronages, becauſe it was written to a perſon of a publique ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of very eminent abilities, and of great authority, by whoſe means it is like it was ſtopped, for after the date of this Letter we no more heard of it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:118678:17"/>
            <head>TO THE Sincere and Pious Preachers of the Word of God, whether ordained Miniſters or gifted Brethren (Expectants or Probatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) for the Miniſtry of the Goſpel.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and welbeloved Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HOw much and how many of you are concerned in the Contents of theſe Papers (now preſented to the publike view) though I do not certainly know, nor have either minde or leiſure curiouſly to enquire, I may probably gueſſe, that all of you (who have been ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Miniſteriall emploiment in divers Congregations ſince the depoſition of Biſhops) may finde your intereſt conſiderably touched in them, though in a different degree: and albeit it be our principal duty to labour unceſſantly, preaching in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. that the <hi>Lord may be magnified,</hi> Pſa. 35.37. <hi>His people and faithfull ſervants multiplied, that daily there may be added to the Church ſuch as ſhould be ſaved,</hi> Act. 2.47. yet is it neither unlawfull nor unbeſeeming the office of the ableſt and holieſt Miniſter, by all warrantable waies, to ſecure his own condition and his Brethrens alſo (ſo far as he may be aſſiſtant to them) from unjuſt moleſtation, eſpecially at ſuch a time as this, when many ſo beſtir themſelves to reduce the Miniſtry to ſuch a deſpicable poverty as may degrade an Evangelical pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicant into a Friar mendicant: To this purpoſe (beſides the buſie malignity of the Levelling ſpirit againſt Miniſters in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall) there hath lately been diſcovered a new device of men (in other things their paſſionate oppoſites) againſt ſome Miniſters in particular, <hi>viz.</hi> by a formality of Law, to eject thoſe who were placed in ſequeſtred Benefices, by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament: which of late neceſſitated M. <hi>Y.</hi> of <hi>K.</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:118678:18"/>in <hi>Leiceſterſhire,</hi> to fly for refuge to his Highneſſe the Lord Protector, and to the ſame <hi>Aſylum,</hi> many more had juſt cauſe to betake themſelves, not only for that they are liable to the like diſturbauce but (beſides that) to the perill of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion upon the death of the outed Miniſters, if the Patron pleaſe not to ſettle them in their places.</p>
            <p>And this being the common condition of many Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> it cannot but appear very conſonant to equity and reaſon, that they ſhould jointly addreſſe their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and Petitions where they may hope to finde remedy, and our hope (at the time of the firſt conſultation of ſome of us about it) was only in his Highneſſe the Lord Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, with his honourable Council; But now the Parliament nearly approaching before we have perfected our addreſſe in that way. we know not whether his Highneſſe (were we as ready as we ſhould be) would not tranſmit our cauſe to the hearing and determination of that venerable Senate, which if he did we ſhould have the better hope of good ſucceſſe in our ſuit, if withall he would vouchſafe (upon our hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Requeſt) to commend it with favour to their conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>In this and other particulars of importance your Brother and Servant (the penman of theſe rather ſerious then cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious dictates) would gladly be adviſed by you, and had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be guided by your Judgement (if he might be ſo happy as to know it) then offer to leade you by his own; yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a buſineſſe of this nature cannot advance to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of many, if it do not commence from the motion of ſome one, having waited a good while, and as yet in vain for an inceptor to ſet it on foot, whoſe footſteps I might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and fearing that the longer we delay to Petition for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour or juſtice, the more prejudice may grow againſt our prevailing therein, as in the caſe betwixt the Iſraelites and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morites, <hi>Judg.</hi> 11.26. (though in a different proportion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the time of forbearance and ſilence) and not knowing for how ſhort a while I may have opportunity to ſerve my generation; I thought it was my duty now to do ſomething in this kinde, and to preſent it to you (my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118678:18"/>for your animadverſion or approbation (as you think moſt meet) I am not ſo ſond as to imagine that in theſe daies (wherein diſſenting conceits make many like beads dropt from a broken ſtring and running out ſeverall waies one from another) that all whom I deſire to gratifie by mine endeavours herein, will be ready to entertain it with equal acceptance: that were to expect a miracle, like that which is written of <hi>mauna</hi> in the book of Wiſedom, <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 20. <hi>viz.</hi> though it were but one kinde of meat, <hi>it was able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent every mans delight, agreeing to every taſte,</hi> or like that language which (though but one ſpoken by the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.6.)<note n="a" place="margin">So in the Annotations of the Old Bible (called the Biſhops Bible.)</note> became the ſame to every hearer, which he underſtood (as ſome by<note n="b" place="margin">Greg. Nazian. Orat. <hi>44.</hi> in Pentecoſt. Tom. <hi>1. p. 715, 716.</hi>
               </note> different pointing give the ſenſe of the words, though by a right point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them (<note n="c" place="margin">Non inſcite dixit eruditus quidam, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam diſtinctionem Commentarij genus eſſe. <hi>Eraſm.</hi> de Recta Latini Gracique ſermonis pronunciat. <hi>p. 63.</hi>
               </note> which in ſome caſes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth inſtead of a Comment) the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be otherwiſe, ſo farre otherwiſe, that it is a Relation no leſſe then ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, which the Papiſts give out of <hi>Francis Xaverius</hi> the Apoſtle of the Indies (as they call him,) <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">So in the lives of the Saints gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Ribadeneira</hi> and <hi>Villegus,</hi> and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Edw Kinſm.</hi> par. 1. p. 34. print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Anno</hi> 1623.</note> 
               <hi>That divers times it happened while he preached there, that men of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Nations heard their own tongue in one Sermon;</hi> But from the diverſity fore mentioned I may expect there may be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who have no minde to have a hand in this matter, though upon ſeverall grounds, on which I will make no conjectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral deſcant that may offend them; I will now take notice on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of one rather doubt then Objection of ſome godly Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which is, Whether it may not be thought an impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the juſt Right and Priviledge of Patrons, to petition for our ſettlement by any authority but their own? But this was their doubt while yet they were acquainted only with the Petition it ſelf, without the Reaſons, Limitations, and Cautions annexed to it, and when they had read the Caſe ſtated, explained and proved, they confidently conceived there was no juſt cauſe by this redreſſe for any Patron (if competently qualified to deſerve the honour of that deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118678:19"/>to be diſpleaſed with us, eſpecially ſince a good part of the plea which we make for our ſelves, is an Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for them againſt thoſe who would have their intereſt in the choice and admiſſion of a Miniſter, laid levell with theirs who are of loweſt rank (it may be alſo their Tenants or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants) in a Parochial Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>Beſides this (I confeſſe) ſome ſcruple may be taken at ſome particular relations, which are known but to few, it may be only to the writer of them, and perhaps to ſome mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes of his the miſpriſions of the Printer may be added.</p>
            <p>But for all that, the ſubſtance of the Petition and Reaſons may be ſound, and aſſent is required to no more, and if the Petition it ſelf be held right, it will be no wrong to the reſt to allow of it alone, yet if any one of better abilities will be pleaſed to undertake the cauſe, and carry it on in ſuch a way as may be capable of more generall compliance, I ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it honour enough to be his forerunner, to prepare the way for his more gracious acceptation, by teſtifying of him, as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> did of Chriſt (though neither of us both be worthy to be compared to either of them) <hi>He that cometh after me is mightier then I,</hi> Mat. 3.11. and both of us may be more likely to prevail then one alone, though if my ſelf ſhould come out ſingle without any atteſtation (which yet hath not been my lot, albeit I have been thrice before now put upon ſuch a ſervice as this in the way of printed publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) it ſhall not diſcourage me, ſince as my chief aim hath been to promote the glory of God and the common good, not only of my contemporaries but of the generation to come, ſo have I (in the preſent addreſſe to the ſuperior pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) ſincerely directed my courſe to the ſame port with the leſſe looking at mine own particular, though in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects my caſe be the ſame with many of yours, becauſe I want not fair hopes of the lawfull favour of potent friends, to winde my ſelf (ſingle) out of the perſonal ſenſe of our principal aggrievance; which if it ſhould fail I may finde an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of you. But the Apoſtles deſcription of Charity by this property with others, <hi>that it ſecketh not her own,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118678:19"/>1 Cor. 13.5.<note n="e" place="margin">Verba <hi>non quaerlt quae ſua ſunt,</hi> ſic intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur, quia communia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prijs, non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria communibus anteponit. Eſtius in <hi>1 Cor. 13.5.</hi> ex. Aug.</note> that is, preferreth a common before a peculiar good, not è <hi>contra,</hi> both enjoyneth and enclineth me to joy more in the ſociable participation of a publike benefit with the reſt of my Brethren, then as a private favour to obtain a grace or indulgence for my ſelf alone. This is the minde of him who heartily praieth to God for you all, that in all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary points of faith, piety, and charity, <hi>you may be of one accord, of one minde,</hi> Phil. 2.2. that <hi>you may ſpeak the ſame thing and be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde and the ſame judgement,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.10. and while thus you live, love, and joyn together (as Brethren) God will own you as his children, and <hi>if children then heirs, heirs of God and joyut heirs with Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 8.17. in this high, holy, and happy communion, it is his only ambition to have a ſhare with you, who while he lives reſolveth to remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Entirely yours, In all the offices of a loving Brother, and humble Servant, <hi>Philotheus Philomyſtes.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aug. 1. 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
